Today, she has decided to play to you Darbari Kanada
Bugün o size Darbari Kanada çalmaya karar verdi
and the tabla is Mr. Balakrishna this is also
ve tabla ise Bay Balakrishna'ya ait, bu da Benim için bir sürpriz oldu,
a surprise to me that from the South Indian
Güney Hindistan'dan bu, görüyorsunuz,
to this, you see, from Aditala to Tritala, it's quite a difference.
Aditala'dan Tritala'ya, oldukça büyük bir fark var.
He speaks Marathi.
Kendisi Marathi konuşuyor.
Marathi means you are then finished in music.
Marathi demek müzikte bitmişsiniz demektir.
Maharashtrians are mad after music, mad.
Maharashtrialılar müzik için deli olurlar, deli.
And this is husband of the great artist,
Ve kendisi büyük sanatçının kocası,
he is another artist's son, I should say.
başka bir sanatçınında oğlu diyebilirim.
May God bless you
Tanrı sizi korusun.
Music 48 min, then speech...
Önce 48 dakika müzik, sonra konuşma...
Musician: I will now render a Banarasi Dadra,
Müzisyen: Şimdi bir Banarasi Dadra çalacağım,
it's a speciality of the place where I come from Banaras.
Banaras'tan, bu geldiğim yerin bir özelliği.
Musician: In the end, I will play Bhairavi
Müzisyen: Sonda Bhairavi çalacağım
and after that, a small Stuti on Shri Mataji.
ve ondan sonra Shri Mataji üzerine küçük bir Stuti.
I will play just one line.
Sadece bir satır çalacağım.
The next will be a Bhajan.
Bir sonraki Bhajan olacak.
The opening words are, ......
Açılış sözleri,…..
After this very, very beautiful concert,
bu çok, çok güzel konserden sonra,
I find it very difficult to express the beauty
keyif aldığımız güzelliği
that we have enjoyed and the delicacy,
ifade etmekte çok zorlanıyorum
all the waves of different hues and colors
ve incelik, farklı tonların
is something I feel that after Her realization,
ve renklerin tüm dalgaları,
She has jumped into another realm, definitely.
O'nun aydınlanma almasından sonra kesinlikle başka bir aleme atladığını hissettiğim bir şey.
As if She was pulling every string of my heart all the time,
Sanki kalbimin her telini her zaman
with such dignity and balance.
böyle bir asalet ve denge ile titretiyordu.
And all of you absolutely lost in the waves
Ve hepiniz O'nunla kurduğunuz o güzel ilişkinin
of that beautiful rapport you had with Her.
dalgaları arasında kayboldunuz.
Our music, I know I have told you
Müziğimiz, size yüzlerce kez
hundred times, comes from the Spirit.
söylediğimi biliyorum, Ruh'tan gelir.
And as you have now felt your Spirit,
Ve şimdi Ruhunuzu hissettiğiniz için,
you can appreciate the joy.
neşeyi takdir edebilirsiniz.
And when the Spirit manifests its light
Ve Ruh ışığını bu güzel melodiler
on these beautiful tunes and melodies,
ve ezgiler üzerinde tezahür ettirdiğinde,
then it gets a very special type of a vision for all of you.
o zaman hepiniz için çok özel bir vizyona dönüşür.
And I am happy you enjoyed Her thoroughly.
Ve kendisinin tadını doyasıya çıkardığınız için mutluyum.
She has got Her realization.
O (bayan) aydınlanmasını aldı.
And you are all Sahaja Yogis, so naturally
Ve hepiniz Sahaja Yogisiniz,
there was great relationship also.
bu yüzden doğal olarak harika bir ilişki de vardı.
Apart from that, I have discovered one thing more today,
Bunun dışında, bugün bir şey daha keşfettim,
that South Indians,
Güney Hindistanlılar müzikle uğraştıklarında,
when they take to music, it's not a profession, it's a worship.
bu bir meslek değil, bir ibadettir.
The purity of rendering the art
Sanatı icra etmenin saflığı sadece O'nda değil,
is so evident, not in Her, but also with Mr. Balakrishna.
Bay Balakrishna'da da çok açık.
Both of them, absolutely, the purity of it.
Her ikisinde de kesinlikle saflık var.
There is no mixture, there is no cheapness, there is no
Karışım yok, ucuzluk yok,
publicity, or sort of a,
reklam yok ya da bir tür, diyebilirsiniz ki,
you can say, modulated things.
modüle edilmiş şeyler yok.
It's just pure art, in the greatest purity.
Bu sadece saf sanat, en büyük saflıkta.
And this is something I discovered today.
Bu da, bugün keşfettiğim bir şey.
We have to learn from South Indians this point,
Güney Hindistanlılardan bu hususu öğrenmeliyiz,
very important, that they render,
bu çok önemli, burada değil
I have seen not here, but even in Madras,
ama Madras'ta bile gördüm, ister dans etsinler,
whether they are dancing, they are playing violin,
ister keman çalsınlar,
or they are playing their Mridangam or anything,
ister Mridangam'larını çalsınlar
it is for them a worship.
ya da herhangi bir şey yapsınlar, bu onlar için bir ibadettir.
Because of that, the purity is maintained.
Bu nedenle saflık korunur.
There is no show off, nothing.
Gösteriş yok, hiçbir şey yok.
So, so deep.
Yani, çok derin.
And today these two artists who are from
Ve bugün Güneyli olan bu iki sanatçı
South have learnt all North Indian music.
tüm Kuzey Hindistan müziğini öğrendiler.
The rendering is so pure, so pure, I mean.
Yorumlama çok saf, çok saf yani.
I was just thinking of some great artists
Dinlediğim bazı büyük sanatçıları düşünüyordum,
whom I have heard, because I must be the oldest woman here.
çünkü buradaki en yaşlı kadın Ben olmalıyım.
And those who have been really very much,
Ve Bana göre gerçekten çok yüksek olan
in My view, the highest,
ya da klasik Kuzey Hindistan müziğimizin özü diyebileceğimiz
or we can call the epitome of our classical North Indian music,
bu sanatçılar,
have been expressed through them today, definitely.
bugün kesinlikle onlar aracılığıyla ifade edildi.
No show off, nothing, it's so beautiful.
Gösteriş yok, hiçbir şey yok, bu çok güzel.
And this is what we have to learn,
Öğrenmemiz gereken şey de bu,
that art is a worship.
sanat bir ibadettir.
It's not a profession.
Bir meslek değildir.
Many people say that those who are pujaris of Saraswati
Pek çok kişi Saraswati'nin pujarisi olanların Lakshmi söz konusu olduğunda
are always in trouble as far as the Lakshmi is concerned.
her zaman başlarının belada olduğunu söyler
But that's your duty to look after their Lakshmi side.
ama onların Lakshmi tarafıyla ilgilenmek sizin göreviniz
But their duty is to be purely devoted,
ama onların görevi tamamen adanmış olmaktır,
dedicated to the art as a worship.
bir ibadet olarak sanata adanmış olmaktır.
And as audience, or you can say as
Ve dinleyiciler olarak
people who are enjoying that music, must look after
ya da o müzikten keyif alan insanlar olarak diyebilirsiniz ki,
their financial side, their Lakshmi side.
kendi finansal taraflarına, kendi Lakshmi taraflarına bakmalıdırlar.
And also always respect, respect the artist.
Ve ayrıca her zaman sanatçıya saygı gösterin, saygı gösterin.
Artist is to be respected because he is
Sanatçıya saygı duyulmalı
worshipping the Goddess Saraswati.
çünkü o Tanrıça Saraswati'ye ibadet ediyor.
I can't understand how people can be disrespectful.
İnsanların nasıl saygısız olabildiğini anlayamıyorum.
And in our country especially I have seen now,
Ve bizim ülkemizde, özellikle de şu anda gördüğüm kadarıyla,
there is such a big trend towards cheap type of music,
ucuz müzik türüne doğru o kadar büyük bir eğilim var ki,
that they just make fun of art.
sanatla dalga geçiyorlar.
As Sahaja Yogis you have to really
Sahaja Yogiler olarak,
understand that this is the music of the Spirit.
bunun Ruhun müziği olduğunu gerçekten anlamalısınız.
Whether it is North or South Indian,
İster Kuzey ister Güney Hint müziği olsun,
I enjoy the same way,
aynı şekilde keyif alıyorum,
whether it is South Indian or North Indian music,
ister Güney Hint ister Kuzey Hint müziği olsun,
makes no difference to Me.
Benim için fark etmiyor.
Both are absolutely supreme in their own style and field.
Her ikisi de kendi tarzlarında ve alanlarında kesinlikle yücedirler.
I don't know what to say about Mrs. Rajam.
Bayan Rajam hakkında ne söyleyeceğimi bilemiyorum.
I met her because of her mother-in -law actually.
Aslında onunla kayınvalidesi sayesinde tanıştım.
And then she has developed so much.
Ve sonra kendisi çok gelişti
But today she was very much different I felt,
ama bugün çok daha farklıydı,
very much closer to Me and closer to all of you.
Bana ve hepinize çok daha yakın olduğunu hissettim.
May God bless you, Mrs. Rajam, your husband and you especially.
Tanrı sizi, Bayan Rajam'ı, eşinizi ve özellikle sizi korusun.
I hope we'll have more chances to listen to your tabla.
Umarım tablanızı dinlemek için daha çok fırsatımız olur.
If you are in Bombay, it should be easier for us
Eğer Bombay'da iseniz, size ulaşmamız daha kolay olacaktır,
to get you, because she is in Banaras.
çünkü o Banaras'ta.
Doesn't matter.
Önemli değil.
We have very small little thing for her.
Onun için çok küçük bir şeyimiz var.
Something for you is a Maharashtrian saree.
Senin için bir Maharashtrian sarisi.
You always wear South Indian sarees,
Sen hep Güney Hindistan sarisi giyersin
but I hope you'll enjoy this one also.
ama umarım bunu da beğenirsin.
And this is for you.
Ve bu da senin için.
I hope to your height it will fit, I mean.
Umarım senin boyuna uyar.
Maharashtrians are not that tall, but they make it quite high things.
Maharashtrialılar o kadar uzun değiller, ama oldukça yüksek şeyler yapıyorlar.
Let's see. Oh, it's all right.
Bakalım. Oh, tamamdır.
And a small little gift from all of us.
Ve hepimizden küçük bir hediye.
You have to go to the village and order it, otherwise you don't get it.
Köye gidip sipariş vermelisiniz, yoksa alamazsınız.
It's very beautiful.
Bu çok güzel.
She has a blouse piece also.
Bir de bluz kısmı da var.